Economics Collection, 1858- 1990
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Economics collection
1858- 1990
MS 432
2 boxes; 1 volume (1 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Collection contains printed materials on economics as it relates to women in the U.S. Types of material include articles, newsletters, pamphlets, resource manuals, court hearings, and symposium proceedings. Includes women in the workforce, as economic equals, and as consumers. Material published by the U. S. Department of Labor, Joint Economic Committee, the U. S. Department of Housing and Urban Development, and the United Nations.
The Economics Collection contains printed materials on economics as it relates to women in the U.S. The collection dates from the mid-nineteenth century to the present, although the majority of the material dates from the 1970s. Types of material include articles, newsletters, pamphlets, resource manuals, court hearings, and symposium proceedings. Topics covered are women in the workforce, women as economic equals, and women as consumers. There are also smaller amounts of material on women and development programs, insurance, pensions, credit discrimination, poverty and welfare, and information/statistics from the U. S. Department of Labor (Women's Bureau). There is also material relating to women published by the Joint Economic Committee, the U. S. Department of Housing and Urban Development, and the United Nations (project achievement reports for U.N. development programs). Nineteenth century materials include books and a pamphlet, "An Appeal to the Women of America" by Desdemona Marke (1858), regarding a protective tariff.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected.
History of the Collection
Materials in this subject collection were either purchased or given to the Sophia Smith Collection by various donors.
Search Terms
Poor women--United States--History--20th century; Working class--United States--History--20th century; Women and development--United States--History--20th century; Women consumers--United States- History--20th century; Women--Economic conditions--United States; Women--Employment--United States--History--20th century
- Articles and printed material, 1910-81, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Pamphlets, 1968-76 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Credit, 1972-75, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Development, 1981-93 (Box 1, Folder 3a)
- Insurance, 1972-78 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Pensions, 1972-80 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Poverty, 1917-82, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Protective tariff: An appeal to the women of America, by Desdemona Marke, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Women and wealth, 1920-31, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Women as consumers, 1919-77, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Proceedings of a symposium: "Women in the Economy," 1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Welfare, 1972-74, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Welfare: clippings, 1972-77 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Books on Shelf
  - Women and Economics by Charlotte Perkins Gilman 1899
  - How to Lay a Nest Egg: Financial Facts for the Average Girl by Edgar Scott 1950